So let's look at a relatively simple
implementation of a barrier in a
program. So this is our barrier
implementation. Our counter is a shared
variable and everybody's trying to
increment it when they arrive to the
barrier. Multiple threads could arrive
to the barrier at about the same time.
So we have to protect the counter using
a lock. So here what we're really doing
is counting the arrivals. Once we are
done incrementing the counter, we can
check if the counter is equal to the
total. If it is, that means that we are
either the last thread or that the last
thread has arrived. Note that the two
are not necessarily the same. We may be
able to increment the counter, but we
are not the last thread, but by the time
we get to check the total, the last
thread has arrived and increments the
counter. So, we read the counter that is
not the same as what we left it with.
Either way, if the counter is equal to
the total, then we reset the counter
because it needs to be reinitialized so
that next time we enter the same barrier
variable, we have the count at zero. And
we set the release flag to one so that
the threads who are waiting find out
that the barrier can now be released. If
the count is not equal to the total,
then we're going to spin here waiting
for somebody else to find that the count
is equal to the total and release. After
we are done going through one instance
of this barrier, the release will be
one. Before we can reuse this barrier,
the release needs to be set at zero. And
that's the purpose of this line here. If
we are the first thread to arrive, then
we're going to set release to zero. So
the idea is now that as we enter the
barrier, the first thread that arrives
and know that this is done in a critical
section. So exactly one thread will see
this as zero. It sets release to zero.
That thread then increments the count,
it becomes one and then goes on here.
That thread and all the other threads
now see release as zero. And the only
way it becomes one is if count reaches
the total. So what happens is the first
thread might actually be delayed and
read the count after everybody is done
in which case it's going to do this or
it might go here and spin. But either
way release becoming one means that
somebody got to this point which is when
the barrier should be released. One or
more threads that arrive towards the end
are going to do this which will reset
the count so that next time we enter we
see count zero and release is set to one
which ensures that those threads that
did end up here are going to see release
as one. Note that the meaning of the
spin release equals 1 is actually that
we wait for release to be one. It turns
out that this barrier code is not
entirely correct. If two threads are
synchronizing on this barrier, the total
will be two and the barrier actually
works the first time. So the thread one
reaches the barrier and so does thread
two. Now they synchronize on this
barrier and that will work. But if we
try to continue work and then
synchronize on the same barrier variable
again, we would expect that this setting
of the count to zero and this setting of
the release to zero to work. But it
doesn't always work. So this is not an
entirely correct implementation of a
barrier that can be used more than once.